Benoît GALLET, Ph.D.

☑ benoit.gallet@nau.edu | 🗓 (928) 433-9008 | in LinkedIn | 🗘 GitHub | 🏶 Website

SUMMARY

Postdoctoral scholar in cybersecurity and computer science/ecoinformatics at Northern Arizona University.

PhD in Informatics and Computing from Northern Arizona University: "Efficient Euclidean Distance Calculations and Distance Similarity Searches: An Examination of Heterogeneous CPU, GPU and Tensor Core Architectures".

Expert in data analysis and clustering algorithms, high-performance computing, parallel and GPU computing, and algorithm performance optimization.

Authored and presented several publications in international conferences.

EXPERIENCE –

Northern Arizona University Postdoctoral Scholar in Cybersecurity

Flagstaff, AZ

Jun 2023 – Jun 2024

• Porting Number Theoretic Transform (NTT) operations from the Post-Quantum Cryptography (PQC) algorithm Kyber from the CPU to GPU Tensor Cores using CUDA.

Postdoctoral Scholar in Computer Science/Ecoinformatics Jun 2023 – Jun 2024

- Designing and coding an algorithm to periodically retrieve satellite image data from several providers (PlanetLabs, NASA, ESA, USGS) for the state of Arizona, using Python.
- Designing and coding an algorithm to periodically ingest newly downloaded imagery, fit data onto a grid spanning Arizona, and update a model to compute the tree water and bark beetle stresses for each pixel. Uses C++, and OpenMPI for distributed computing.

Graduate Research Assistant

Aug 2018 – May 2023

- Worked on data analysis and clustering algorithms, in particular those computing similarity searches using the Euclidean distance.
- Designed several GPU algorithms and optimizations; a heterogeneous CPU-GPU algorithm; and a novel GPU algorithm using Tensor Cores to compute distance similarity searches.
- Published and presented several articles in international conferences.
- Related to the PhD dissertation.

CS450 Instructor

May 2022 - Aug 2022

- Instructor of record for the CS450 Instruction to Parallel Programming class for the summer 2022 term.
- Taught shared memory parallelism, including pthreads and OpenMP.
- Average course evaluation: 3.86 / 4.

Université d'Orléans MSc Internship

Orléans, France Apr 2018 – Sep 2018

- GPU Kernel Performance Optimizations for Efficient Similarity Joins.
- Proposed several optimizations for a GPU distance similarity searches algorithm.

Université d'Orléans / National Center for Scientific Research Orléans, France BSc Internship Apr 2016 – Jun 2016

- GPU Detection of Pulse Radio Signals.
- Cleaned and formatted an existing sequential CPU code in C detecting pulse radio signals from neutron stars with a radio telescope.
- Ported the original code to the GPU using CUDA.

EDUCATION –

Northern Arizona University PhD in Informatics and Computing

Flagstaff, AZ 2023

- Efficient Euclidean Distance Calculations And Distance Similarity Searches: An Examination of Heterogeneous CPU, GPU, and Tensor Core Architectures, supervised by Dr. Michael Gowanlock.
- Worked as a Graduate Research Assistant.
- Published 4 articles as first author, presented in several international conferences.

Université d'Orléans MSc in Computer Science

Orléans, France 2018

· With Honors.

Université d'Orléans BSc in Computer Science Orléans, France 2016

SKILLS -

- C, C++, Python, CUDA, OpenMP, MPI.
- Data analysis and clustering algorithms, high-performance computing, parallel and GPU computing, algorithms, data structures, performance optimizations.
- · Conducting research, presenting, public speaking.
- French (native), English (bilingual), German (intermediate).

PUBLICATIONS —

- Michael Gowanlock, Benoit Gallet and Brian Donnelly, Optimization and Comparison of Coordinate- and Metric-Based Indexes on GPUs for Distance Similarity Searches. Proceedings of the International Conference on Computational Science (ICCS), pp. 357-364. doi: 10.1007/978-3-031-36021-3_37, Prague, Czech Republic, July 2023.
- 2. **Benoit Gallet** and Michael Gowanlock, *Leveraging GPU Tensor Cores for Double Precision Euclidean Distance Calculations*. Proceedings of the 29th IEEE International Conference on High Performance Computing, Data, and Analytics (HiPC), pages 135–144, doi: 10.1109/HiPC56025.2022.00029, Bengaluru, India, December 2022.
- Michael Gowanlock and Benoit Gallet, Data-Intensive Computing Modules for Teaching Parallel and Distributed Computing. NSF/TCPP Workshop on Parallel and Distributed Computing Education, Proceedings of the IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium Workshops (IPDPSW), pages 350–357, doi: 10.1109/IPDPSW52791.2021.00062, Portland, USA, June 2021.
- 4. **Benoit Gallet** and Michael Gowanlock, *Heterogeneous CPU-GPU Epsilon Grid Joins: Static and Dynamic Work Partitioning Strategies*. Data Science and Engineering, Volume 6, pages 39–62, doi: 10.1007/s41019-020-00145-x, October 2020.

- 5. **Benoit Gallet** and Michael Gowanlock, *HEGJoin: Heterogeneous CPU-GPU Epsilon Grids for Accelerated Distance Similarity Join.* Proceedings of the 25th International Conference on Database Systems for Advanced Applications (DASFAA), pages 372–388, doi: 10.1007/978-3-030-59419-0_23, Jeju, South Korea, September 2020.
- 6. **Benoit Gallet** and Michael Gowanlock, *Load Imbalance Mitigation Optimizations for GPU-Accelerated Similarity Joins*. IEEE High-Performance Big Data, Deep Learning, and Cloud Computing Workshop, Proceedings of the 2019 IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium Workshops (IPDPSW), pages 396–405, doi: 10.1109/IPDPSW.2019.00078, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, May 2019 (Best Paper Award).

POSTER PRESENTATIONS -

- 1. **Benoit Gallet** and Michael Gowanlock, *Optimizing GPU-Accelerated Similarity Joins Addressing Data-Dependent Workloads*. IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS), PhD Forum, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 2019.
- 2. **Benoit Gallet** and Michael Gowanlock, *Exploring The Design-Space of GPU-Efficient Similarity Self-Join Kernels*. High-Level Parallel Programming and Applications (HLPP), 11th International Symposium, Orléans, France, 2018.

SERVICE -

- Co-supervised MSc student research projects at Northern Arizona University (Flagstaff, USA) and University of Orléans (Orléans, France).
- Co-designed a Python coding course for the Tuba City high school.
- External reviewer for the International Conference on Computational Science (ICCS): 2020–2023.
- Reviewer for the Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing (JPDC), Elsevier.
- Reviewer for the IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE) journal.
- Reviewer for the Journal of Statistical Software.